Guide to the World Citizens Association. Chicago Group Records 1939-1943
University of Chicago Library
World Citizens Association. Chicago Group. Records
1939-1943
5 linear feet (10 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The World Citizens Association was an outgrowth of attempts to found an American division of the World Foundation. Founded in 1939 under the patronage of Anita McCormick Blaine, the Chicago Group was disbanded in 1943 for lack of funding. Carleton Washburne chaired the group. The Chicago Group prepared surveys or study kits dealing with international cooperation. Contains correspondence, by-laws, minutes, reports, financial records, surveys, and membership information. Contains files of executive director, Edwin M. Clough. Correspondents include Anita McCormick Blaine, Quincy Wright, Edwin Cassels, Jerome Kerwin, and others. Material relates to the group's activities in promoting international cooperation and organization.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The World Citizens Association was an outgrowth of S. de Maderiaga's attempts at founding an American division of the World Foundation. Founded in 1939 under the patronage of Mrs. Anita McCormick Blaine, the Chicago group was dissolved in 1943 for lack of sufficient operating funds. In the course of its life under the chairmanship of Carleton Washburne, superintendent of schools in Winnetka, and under the executive directorship of Edwin M. Clough (1939-1940), John R. Van de Water (1940-1943), and Caroline Willis (1943), the Chicago Group prepared eleven surveys/study kits on as many different subjects having some relation to international cooperation. The World Citizens Association actively encouraged the development of groups to use these materials or sponsored them in order to come to some understanding and opinion as to the practicality, possibility, and nature of the post-war "organization" of the world.
Scope Note
The Records are divided into five series. Series I contains general correspondence. Series II is a group of files compiled by Edwin M. Clough during his tenure as director. Series III contains the organization's financial records; Series IV is a selection of replies received to requests for literature for the Committee's surveys. Series V comprises file cards on various publications.
The Records of the World Citizens Association, Central Committee should be consulted in conjunction with this collection.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
World Citizens Association. Central Committee. Records
Subject Headings
Blaine, Anita McCormick; Cassels, Edwin Henry, 1874-; Clough, Edwin M.; Kerwin, Jerome G. (Jerome Gregory), 1896-; Washburne, Carleton, b. 1889; Wright, Quincy, 1890-1970; World Citizens Association. Chicago Group; International cooperation; Internationalism; International organization; International organization -- Societies, etc.; International relations
INVENTORY
- Series I: General Correspondence
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-Laws, Chicago Group (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Current Work (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Discussion Subjects (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Donnelley and Son, R. R. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee, Monday, October 13, WCA, Chicago Group (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, Minutes (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, Minutes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Austin, Mrs. Henry (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blaine, Mrs. Emmons (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cassels, Edwin H. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Colegrove, Kenneth (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gilkey, Mrs Charles W. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Goodman, Howard (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kerwin, Jerome (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Laves, Walter A. C. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lawrence, Mrs. Clark J. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lloyd, William B. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Schoerb, Dr. Rolland (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Smith, Herbert W. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Smith, Perry Dunlap (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Washburne, Carleton (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Williamson, Burke (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Weinstein, Rabbi Jacob (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Wright, Quincy (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - F (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Faculty Advisory Committee, Student Council on World Citizenship (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Films (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Films for Meetings (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Financial Drive Returns (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Form Letters (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - H (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - High School Weekend Conference (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - I (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Inquiries, in re Organizations (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Interested in Study, A-L (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Interested in Study, M-Z (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - International Relations Center Plan (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - International Student Service Literature (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Inventories (Chicago Group) and Equipment (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Invoices for Literature, Paid (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - J (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - K (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - L (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Labor (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Literature, Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mc (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - M (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - N (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - O (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Organizations (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Orchestra Hall Meeting, Accounts (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Publicity, Orchestra Hall Meeting, Committee on World Organization, 8 December 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings: In Time of War Prepare for Peace, corrected for publication (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Proceedings: In Time of War Prepare for Peace, carbon copy (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Orchestra Hall Meeting, A-L (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Orchestra Hall Meeting, M-Z (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Owentsia Conference (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - P (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Petition: Illinois Legislative Program (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pictographs (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Discussion Group Questions (Problems for Study and Discussion) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Publications (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Publicity, in re World Citizens Association (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Q (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - R (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Radio (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Radio Folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Rockford Group (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - S (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Speaker's Teams, WCA, I (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Speaker's Teams, WCA, II (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Speaking Trip Arrangements (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Student Council (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Student Council on World Citizenship, University of Chicago Group (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Study Kit Orders (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - First Survey (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Second Survey (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Third Survey (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Fourth Survey (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Fifth Survey (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Sixth Survey (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Seventh Survey (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Eighth Survey (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ninth Survey (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Tenth Survey (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Eleventh Survey (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - T (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Topeka, Kansas, Discussion Group (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - U (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - V (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Victory News Letter, Requests for Information or Subscription (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Victory News Letter (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Van De Water, John R. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - W-Wi (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Wo-Wr (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - World Citizen (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - WCA, Central Committee (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - WCA, Chicago Group (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - WCA, Chicago Group By-Laws (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - WCA, Instructions to Local Committee (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - XYZ (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Series II: Edwin M. Clough Files
  - B (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Badges (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - C, 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Carnegie Foundation (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Council on International Relations (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - (Proposals to Executive Committee) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Form Letters, WCA, Chicago Group (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - G (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - H (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Hull House Investigation Project (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - International Films (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Inter Office Communications (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Library of International Relations (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - M (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Membership Cards, Chicago Group (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Summaries of the Discussions of the North Shore Group Meetings (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - S (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Smith, Perry Dunlap (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - T (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Tchou-Reports on Meetings, Names of Those Interested at Meeting (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Tchou Groups (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Tchou-Material on Organization of WCA, Tchou, and Wilkins (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - U (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Union Now (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - W (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Washburne, Carleton (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Wright, Quincy (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Series III: Financial Files, Chicago Group
  - Account Book (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Invoices and Expenditures previous to June 1939 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Financial Reports, June 1939-November 1942, including Budget Proposals for 1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - January 1943 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - February 1943 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - March 1943 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - April 1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - May 1943 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - June 1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - July 1943 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - August 1943 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - September 1943 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Audit, August 20, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Harris Trust and Savings Bank (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - City National Bank (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Budgets and Audits (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Series IV: Replies to Requests for Literature for Surveys
  - Form Letter, Request for Publications, Publishers' Lists (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - A-B (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - C-D (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - E-F (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - G-H (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - I-J (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - K-L (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - M-N (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - O-P (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Q-R (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - S-T (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - U-V (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - W-Z (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Series V: File Cards on Publications
  - File cards (Box 10)
  - U (Box 10)